☆独家制作☆
喜马拉雅主播 & 微信公众号:
美国青少年英语
仅供交流学习  禁止商用盈利
地球脉动 III
SNUFFLING
吸鼻
Sauraha, Nepal.
尼泊尔索拉哈。
SNUFFLES AND GRUNTS
鼻塞和咕噜声
HORN BEEPS
喇叭蜂鸣声
DOG WHIMPERS
狗呜咽声
This rhino is not lost.
这头犀牛并没有迷路。
He is on his way to find food.
他正在去寻找食物的路上。
To get it, he must travel through a new and alien world.
为了得到它，他必须穿越一个新的陌生世界。
This rhino in his lifetime
这头犀牛在其一生中
has seen more changes than any of his previous generations.
比他的前几代人经历了更多的变化。
Across the globe,
在全球范围内，
animals of all kinds are now contending
现在各种动物都在争夺
with one newly dominant species...
一个新的优势物种...
..us.
..我们。
HORN BEEPS, SIREN WAILS
喇叭声、警报声
Like so many wild creatures, he's had to learn
像许多野生动物一样，他必须学习
how to live in the human world.
如何在人类世界中生存。
人类
Some animals
一些动物
have changed their behaviour
改变了他们的行为
to make the most out of living amongst us.
充分利用我们之间的生活。
These long-tailed macaques live in Bali.
这些长尾猕猴生活在巴厘岛。
They have developed new interests
他们发展了新的兴趣
brought by human visitors.
由人类访客带来。
Every morning, the troop heads for a building
每天早上，部队都会前往一座建筑物
in the centre of their territory.
在他们领土的中心。
Uluwatu Temple.
乌鲁瓦图寺。
MACAQUES SCREECH
猕猴尖叫
Tourists come here every day - in crowds.
每天都有成群结队的游客来到这里。
So the temple grounds are full of opportunities...
所以寺庙里充满了机会......
..if you know where to look.
..如果您知道去哪里寻找。
WOMAN GASPS
女人喘息
There is a constant supply of hats...
帽子的供应源源不断……
..and sunglasses.
..还有太阳镜。
And if you've mastered the element of surprise...
如果你已经掌握了惊喜的元素......
..it's easy to get them.
……很容易得到它们。
But this harvest is not for eating.
但这个收获不是用来吃的。
It's for bargaining.
是为了讨价还价。
Seems like a fair trade.
看起来像是公平交易。
But there are greater rewards to be had
但还有更大的回报
for those who know how to get them.
对于那些知道如何获得它们的人。
CAMERA SHUTTERS CLICK
相机快门点击
And this old male appears to be doing...
而这个老男人似乎正在做……
..very well.
..很好。
He and the other elders in this troop
他和这支队伍中的其他长老
have both experience and knowledge.
既有经验又有知识。
They've been working the temple for over ten years,
他们在寺庙里工作了十多年，
and now concentrate on the big stuff...
现在专注于大事......
..things that human beings just can't do without.
..人类离不开的东西。
WOMAN GASPS
女人喘息
No-one wants to walk home with just one shoe.
没有人愿意只穿一只鞋走路回家。
WOMAN GASPS
女人喘息
And these old boys can't wait
这些老男孩已经等不及了
to get their hands on the latest tech.
让他们掌握最新的技术。
SHE EXCLAIMS
她感叹道
They've worked out that we simply can't survive
他们发现我们根本无法生存
without our phones...
没有我们的手机...
..or our wallets.
..或者我们的钱包。
WOMAN EXCLAIMS
女人惊呼
MACAQUE SCREECHES
猕猴尖叫声
WOMAN GASPS
女人喘息
The older males understand
年长的男性都明白
something the youngsters have yet to learn...
年轻人还没有学到的东西......
..the art of the deal.
..交易的艺术。
A banana?
一根香蕉？
How dare you!
你怎么敢！
MACAQUE SCREECHES
猕猴尖叫声
A bar of chocolate?
一块巧克力？
That's better.
这样更好。
The real skill is in the negotiations.
真正的技巧在于谈判。
The macaques are playing us at our own game.
猕猴正在玩我们自己的游戏。
They demand...
他们要求...
..whatever they want.
..无论他们想要什么。
Humanity has spread to every corner of the globe.
人类已经传播到地球的每一个角落。
We have become a force of nature.
我们已经成为自然的力量。
We have altered 80% of the land's surface.
我们已经改变了80%的土地表面。
Eight billion people now live on this planet...
现在有八十亿人生活在这个星球上......
..and we are changing the world around us
..我们正在改变我们周围的世界
at such speed...
以这样的速度...
..that, for animals, the challenge is to keep up.
..对于动物来说，挑战是跟上。
New York City.
纽约市。
Ants.
蚂蚁。
This particular species is thought to have arrived here
人们认为这个特殊的物种已经到达这里
with the first European settlers.
与第一批欧洲定居者一起。
They are now known as pavement ants
他们现在被称为路面蚂蚁
because they live almost exclusively in our towns and cities.
因为他们几乎只住在我们的城镇里。
And they're thriving because of junk food.
他们因垃圾食品而蓬勃发展。
And here on Broadway Avenue,
而在百老汇大街这里，
there's a lot of it.
有很多。
This is what every pavement ant desires.
这是每只路面蚂蚁所渴望的。
And to get it...
并且为了得到它...
..the ants use the city's thousands of miles
..蚂蚁利用城市的数千英里
of underground tunnels.
的地下隧道。
This scout is closing in on its target.
这名侦察兵正在逼近目标。
But the animals with which they share the pavement
但与他们共享人行道的动物
are 40 million times their weight...
是其体重的4000万倍...
FOOTSTEPS STOMP
脚步跺脚
..so it's best to stay in the cracks.
……所以最好留在夹缝中。
Jackpot!
大奖！
A meat mountain.
一座肉山。
This is too big a job for just one ant.
对于一只蚂蚁来说，这项工作太大了。
This worker is female,
这位工人是女性，
as they are in all ant colonies,
就像所有的蚁群一样，
and she leaves a trail of pheromones to mark a path.
她会留下一条信息素的痕迹来标记一条路径。
She communicates with every sister she meets
她和她遇到的每一个姐妹都有交流
as she returns to the nest,
当她回到巢穴时，
and news on the street spreads fast.
街上的消息传得很快。
This ultra-processed meat
这种超加工肉
is very different from their original food.
和他们原来的食物有很大不同。
But their digestive system is the key to their success.
但他们的消化系统是他们成功的关键。
It's able to keep up with the way
它能够跟得上路
humans constantly change their diet.
人类不断改变饮食习惯。
Nowadays, the vast majority of what they eat
如今，他们吃的绝大多数东西
comes from human food.
来自人类食物。
On Broadway alone,
仅在百老汇，
pavement ants eat the equivalent
路面蚂蚁吃等量的食物
of a staggering 60,000 hot dogs every year.
每年生产 60,000 只热狗，数量惊人。
The calories in a single hot dog
一个热狗的热量
could fuel the growth
可以推动增长
of the entire ant colony for a month...
整个蚁群一个月......
..if only they can get it back to the nest.
..如果他们能把它带回巢就好了。
But this slow work makes them vulnerable.
但这种缓慢的工作使他们变得脆弱。
PIGEON COOS
鸽子咕咕
They aren't the only ones partial to fast food.
他们并不是唯一偏爱快餐的人。
It's a race to get their prize home.
这是一场将奖品带回家的竞赛。
There may be losses...
可能会有损失...
..but the colony as a whole will now thrive.
.....但整个殖民地现在将会蓬勃发展。
In fact, pavement ants are so successful here
事实上，路面蚂蚁在这里非常成功
that they outnumber human New Yorkers 1,000 to 1.
他们的人数比纽约人多 1,000 比 1。
PIGEONS COO
鸽子首席运营官
But success in the human world can be harder to achieve
但人类世界的成功可能更难
if your reputation precedes you.
如果你的声誉领先于你。
Here in India,
在印度这里，
this cobra is heading directly for a village.
这条眼镜蛇正直奔一个村庄。
It has detected the scent of prey.
它已经嗅到了猎物的气味。
Nearly two metres long,
近两米长，
it has enough venom in a single bite
它一口就有足够的毒液
to kill ten people.
杀死十个人。
Snake bites are responsible
蛇咬伤是罪魁祸首
for nearly 60,000 deaths a year
每年造成近 60,000 人死亡
in India alone.
仅在印度。
They travel so silently
他们如此默默地旅行
that their presence is often undetected.
他们的存在常常未被发现。
And when they are hunting...
而当他们狩猎时...
..there is no place they won't go.
……没有他们不会去的地方。
A toad.
一只蟾蜍。
Each tip of its forked tongue
它分叉的舌头的每一个尖端
collects chemical signals from the prey
收集猎物的化学信号
and helps to reveal its position.
并有助于揭示其立场。
But up close...
但近距离...
COBRA HISSES
眼镜蛇嘶嘶声
..the snake relies on movement
..蛇依靠运动
to precisely locate its prey.
来精确定位猎物。
The toad must pick its moment to escape.
蟾蜍必须选择逃跑的时机。
Every time it touches the ground...
每次接触地面的时候...
..the toad leaves behind a scent.
..蟾蜍留下气味。
It can hide...
它可以隐藏...
..but the trail will lead the snake to it.
……但这条踪迹会把蛇引向那里。
These cobras don't just hunt here.
这些眼镜蛇不只是在这里狩猎。
They live here.
他们住在这里。
They have found a home where the Hindu villagers revere them
他们找到了印度教村民尊敬他们的家
and consider them to be demigods.
并认为他们是半神。
Remarkably, scientists believe that this tolerance
值得注意的是，科学家认为这种耐受性
has led to a change in the snakes' behaviour.
导致了蛇行为的改变。
They move more slowly
他们移动得更慢
and are less likely to strike if disturbed.
如果受到干扰，则不太可能发起攻击。
One of the most feared animals on the planet
地球上最可怕的动物之一
has found a place where they are accepted
已经找到了一个可以接受他们的地方
and can coexist with human beings.
并且可以与人类共存。
But for many animals living in the human world,
但对于生活在人类世界的许多动物来说，
it pays to keep a low profile.
保持低调是值得的。
Here in Melbourne, Australia,
在澳大利亚墨尔本这里，
one creature has perfected the art of camouflage.
有一种生物已经完善了伪装艺术。
A frogmouth chick.
一只蛙口小鸡。
Its father helps to hide it during the day.
它的父亲白天帮忙把它藏起来。
CHICK SQUAWKS
小鸡的叫声
They are nocturnal birds,
它们是夜行性鸟类，
and as day turns to night,
随着白天变成夜晚，
its parents come out of the shadows
它的父母从阴影中走出来
to reap the rewards of urban living.
获得城市生活的回报。
The city lights create
城市灯光创造
excellent conditions for hunting.
狩猎条件优越。
Every night in the city
城市里的每个夜晚
is as bright as when there is a full moon.
如同满月时一样明亮。
BIRD SQUAWKS
鸟叫声
So city frogmouths often...
所以城市蛙口经常...
..have their mouths full.
……他们的嘴都塞满了。
He's growing fast, and today he just won't sit still.
他成长得很快，今天他不会坐以待毙。
DOG BARKS
狗叫声
And now he has revealed his presence.
现在他已经暴露了他的存在。
The first rule of frogmouth behaviour is
蛙口行为的第一条规则是
don't move in the day.
白天不要动。
But this is the one time in a frogmouth's life
但这是蛙口一生中的一次
when the urge to fly simply cannot be suppressed.
当想要飞翔的冲动根本无法抑制的时候。
DOG PANTS
狗裤
BEAK CLICKS, DOG BARKS
喙的声音、狗的叫声
But he's not ready to leave home just yet.
但他还没有准备好离开家。
Come night-time...
晚上来...
..he's hungry again.
……他又饿了。
He is wide awake...
他已经完全清醒了……
..and wants to take off where he left off.
..并想从他离开的地方开始。
But he's getting unwanted attention,
但他却受到了不必要的关注
and this time his parent is not nearby to protect him.
这次他的父母不在附近保护他。
Humans bring pets,
人类带着宠物，
and cats in Australia kill a million birds a day.
澳大利亚的猫每天杀死一百万只鸟。
COLLAR BELL TINKLES
领铃叮当响
His first proper flight.
他的第一次正确飞行。
But unless he can find a safe place to roost,
但除非他能找到一个安全的栖息地
he is still in peril.
他仍然处于危险之中。
Made it.
做好了。
But if he is to survive in the city, like the adults,
但如果他要像大人一样在城市里生存，
he'll have to learn how to blend in.
他必须学会如何融入。
Some animals are so bold
有些动物就是这么大胆
that they don't even try to hide.
他们甚至不想隐藏。
To see a large predator in the built-up world is a rare sight.
在建筑群中看到大型掠食者是罕见的景象。
And here in Lake Tahoe, in North America,
在北美的太浩湖，
these black bears are particularly big...
这些黑熊特别大……
..and they're heading right to the centre of town.
……他们正前往市中心。
BEAR CHOMPS
熊咀嚼物
Winter is approaching,
冬天即将来临，
and these bears need to put on as much weight as possible
这些熊需要增加尽可能多的体重
before the snow arrives.
在雪到来之前。
This is a great place to gorge.
这是一个饱餐一顿的好地方。
HORN BLARES
喇叭声
It's now bear country.
现在是熊国。
FENCE CREAKS
栅栏吱吱作响
Why struggle for a meal...
何必为了一顿饭而苦苦挣扎……
..when you can cross the street...
..当你可以过马路时...
..for a takeaway?
……外卖？
There's so much food here
这里有这么多食物
that some of the bears are 50% heavier
有些熊重 50%
than their country cousins.
比他们的乡下表兄弟。
But why stop here?
但为什么停在这里呢？
Some bears just want to dine in.
有些熊只是想在里面吃饭。
WOMAN GASPS
女人喘息
A lucky few are able to get an easy meal from the human world.
少数幸运者能够从人类世界轻松获得一顿美餐。
But when WE venture to the natural world in search of food...
但是当我们冒险到自然世界寻找食物时......
..the harvest is on a different scale.
……收获的规模不同。
In just four decades,
短短四十年的时间，
fishing reduced fish populations by half...
捕鱼使鱼类数量减少了一半...
..and created great problems for the ocean predators
..给海洋掠食者带来了很大的问题
that once had such food to themselves.
曾经有过这样的食物。
SHIP'S HORN BLOWS
船的号角吹响
Off the coast of Vancouver Island,
在温哥华岛海岸附近，
humpback whales inhabit waters
座头鲸栖息于水域
where herring have been overfished.
那里的鲱鱼被过度捕捞。
Humpbacks, however, are renowned for their ingenuity.
然而，座头鲸以其聪明才智而闻名。
12 years ago, an adult male called Conger
12年前，一位名叫Conger的成年男性
adopted a totally new way of feeding.
采用了全新的喂养方式。
When the density of fish in the water is low,
当水中鱼的密度较低时，
and birds are diving to catch them...
鸟儿们潜入水中捕捉它们......
..the humpback opens its mouth
..座头鲸张开嘴
and creates a space that the fish mistake for shelter.
并创造一个被鱼误认为庇护所的空间。
The fish swim in...
鱼儿游在...
..and the trap is closed.
……陷阱就关闭了。
Conger was the first humpback whale to be seen doing this.
海康格鲸是第一头被发现这样做的座头鲸。
Now 30 whales in the area use this same technique.
现在该地区有 30 头鲸鱼使用同样的技术。
The population of humpbacks here is growing,
这里的座头鲸数量正在增长，
and you might think that this would
你可能认为这会
reduce fish stocks even more,
进一步减少鱼类资源，
but something surprising is thought to be happening.
但人们认为令人惊讶的事情正在发生。
These tiny phytoplankton are the basis of the food chain
这些微小的浮游植物是食物链的基础
and need a vital ingredient to grow.
并且需要重要的成分才能生长。
Iron.
铁。
Whale faeces are rich in iron...
鲸鱼的粪便富含铁...
..and great whales produce it in enormous quantities...
..大鲸鱼大量生产它...
..so the phytoplankton flourishes, and herring feed on it.
..所以浮游植物繁盛，鲱鱼以它为食。
Whale faeces, in fact,
事实上，鲸鱼的粪便
are helping to restore the whole ecosystem.
正在帮助恢复整个生态系统。
The herring attract seabirds,
鲱鱼吸引海鸟，
diving birds attack them from beneath,
潜水的鸟从下面攻击它们，
and gulls and shearwaters dive on them from above.
海鸥和海鸥从上面俯冲到它们身上。
Even bald eagles benefit from this rich feast.
即使是秃鹰也能从这场丰盛的盛宴中受益。
Astonishingly, even though Conger and all the other whales
令人惊讶的是，尽管康格鲸和所有其他鲸鱼
are feasting on fish,
正在大口吃鱼，
their role in fertilising the ocean is so influential
他们在海洋施肥方面的作用是如此有影响力
that herring numbers here are actually predicted to increase.
这里的鲱鱼数量实际上预计会增加。
And the role they play in rejuvenating the environment...
以及它们在恢复环境活力方面发挥的作用......
..is having an even greater impact on the human world.
.....对人类世界产生更大的影响。
The flourishing plankton also collects carbon
繁盛的浮游生物也收集碳
from the atmosphere, just as trees do...
从大气中，就像树一样......
..so much so that each great whale
..如此之多以至于每头鲸鱼
has the same impact as a forest of 30,000 trees.
与拥有 30,000 棵树的森林具有相同的影响。
Our great whales were once hunted...
我们的大鲸鱼曾经被猎杀......
..and if they return to their pre-whaling numbers,
..如果它们恢复到捕鲸前的数量，
it's estimated that this would be equivalent to planting
估计这相当于种草了
over 30 billion trees.
超过300亿棵树。
Whales are now being recognised as benefiting humanity.
鲸鱼现在被认为对人类有益。
But for most large animals,
但对于大多数大型动物来说
competition with humans brings conflict.
与人类的竞争会带来冲突。
This six-tonne African bull elephant is in his prime.
这头六吨重的非洲公象正处于鼎盛时期。
ELEPHANT GRUNTS
大象咕噜声
To stand the best chance of winning fights for females,
为了获得女性赢得战斗的最佳机会，
he needs to be big.
他需要变得很大。
He can smell highly nutritious food is near.
他能闻到附近有营养丰富的食物的味道。
But crossing the boundary to reach it
但跨越界限才能到达
is a dangerous journey.
这是一次危险的旅程。
He must wait for the cover of darkness.
他必须等待黑暗的掩护。
FIRE CRACKLES
火爆裂纹
These Kenyan farmers are preparing for the night ahead.
这些肯尼亚农民正在为即将到来的夜晚做准备。
They have had to guard their crops every night
他们必须每天晚上看守他们的庄稼
for the last two months.
过去两个月。
With only two days until harvest,
距离收获只剩两天了，
this is a critical time.
这是一个关键时刻。
MAN SHOUTS
男人喊叫
In a single night,
在一个晚上，
a bull elephant can destroy the entire crops
一头公象可以毁掉整个庄稼
produced by ten farmers.
由十个农民生产。
SHOUTING
喊叫
ELEPHANT ROARS
大象咆哮
MAN SHOUTS
男人喊叫
But he's taking a huge risk.
但他冒着巨大的风险。
ELEPHANT ROARS
大象咆哮
SHOUTING
喊叫
ELEPHANT SCREECHES
大象的尖叫声
SHOUTING
喊叫
ELEPHANT ROARS
大象咆哮
ELEPHANT TRUMPETS
大象喇叭
ELEPHANT ROARS
大象咆哮
He's twice the height of a man...
他的身高是人类的两倍...
ELEPHANT ROARS
大象咆哮
..and he won't back down easily.
……他不会轻易退缩。
SHOUTING
喊叫
This human-wildlife conflict happens night after night.
人类与野生动物的冲突日复一日地发生。
And each year, it takes the lives
每年，它都会夺走生命
of up to 200 elephants and 20 people in Kenya alone.
仅在肯尼亚就有多达 200 头大象和 20 个人。
LOW RUMBLING
低沉的隆隆声
This standoff is potentially lethal.
这种对峙可能是致命的。
The farmers have had to call for help
农民们不得不打电话求助
from a team of highly experienced rangers.
来自经验丰富的护林员团队。
Although they're armed,
虽然他们全副武装，
their task is to drive the elephant out of the field
他们的任务是将大象赶出田野
without harming it.
而不伤害它。
But the bull is determined...
但公牛决心...
ELEPHANT TRUMPETS
大象喇叭
..to hold ground.
……坚守阵地。
LOW RUMBLING
低沉的隆隆声
The rangers will have to get closer...
护林员将不得不靠近......
ELEPHANT ROARS
大象咆哮
..on foot.
..徒步。
ELEPHANT GROWLS
大象咆哮
LOW RUMBLING
低沉的隆隆声
The rangers have to resort... FIRECRACKER BANGS
护林员必须采取...爆竹爆炸声
ELEPHANT GROWLS ...to firecrackers.
大象咆哮......鞭炮声。
FIRECRACKER BANGS, ELEPHANT ROARS
鞭炮声、大象吼声
ELEPHANT GROWLS
大象咆哮
The bull is driven from this field...
公牛被赶出了这片土地......
ELEPHANT GROWLS
大象咆哮
..and retreats deep into the bush.
……然后撤退到灌木丛深处。
Fortunately for this bull,
对于这头公牛来说幸运的是，
the battle has been resolved peacefully.
战斗已经和平解决。
And efforts like these are seeing fewer elephants killed,
诸如此类的努力减少了大象被杀的情况，
and their population in Kenya is starting to rise again.
肯尼亚的人口又开始增加。
But conflict with wildlife
但与野生动物发生冲突
is now occurring on a far greater scale
现在正在以更大的规模发生
as a consequence
作为结果
of the way we are changing the world's climate.
我们正在改变世界气候的方式。
Some arid regions
一些干旱地区
are now experiencing unusually high rainfall.
现在正在经历异常高的降雨量。
And that is good for growing crops
这对农作物生长有好处
here in northeastern Africa.
这里是非洲东北部。
But it's also the perfect conditions
但这也是完美的条件
for one particular insect.
对于一种特定的昆虫。
Desert locusts.
沙漠蝗虫。
They're normally solitary creatures,
它们通常是独居动物，
but emerging from the sand in great numbers
但大量地从沙子里冒出来
triggers a dramatic physical change.
引发剧烈的身体变化。
They turn a vivid yellow
它们变成鲜艳的黄色
and become highly social.
并变得高度社交。
Together, they are an unstoppable army.
他们在一起就是一支不可阻挡的军队。
On foot, they can cover a mile a day.
步行，他们每天可以走一英里。
But they can only go so far in this way.
但他们只能以这种方式走这么远。
They need to find height.
他们需要找到高度。
Up here, they begin their final transformation.
在这里，他们开始了最后的转变。
Normally, it takes an individual insect
通常，需要单个昆虫
at least a month to become a winged adult...
至少要一个月才能成为有翅膀的成年人……
..but in their social form, their development speeds up.
..但在他们的社会形式中，他们的发展速度加快。
SQUELCHING
压制
Now all they need is for their wings to harden.
现在他们所需要的只是让翅膀变硬。
Once airborne, they can travel 60 miles in a day.
一旦升空，他们一天可以飞行 60 英里。
Swarms merge and they become a plague.
蜂群合并，成为瘟疫。
This one contains billions of individuals,
这其中包含了数十亿个人，
and eats as much in a day
一天吃那么多
as the entire population of Germany.
相当于德国的全部人口。
Today in northeastern Africa,
今天在非洲东北部，
as a consequence of climate change...
由于气候变化...
..devastating surges of locusts
..毁灭性的蝗虫激增
are becoming more frequent.
变得越来越频繁。
Two worlds are colliding.
两个世界正在碰撞。
Unintentionally, humanity has created exactly the conditions
人类无意中创造了这样的条件
that cause this species to explode in numbers.
导致该物种数量爆炸。
But another group of animals has seen
但另一群动物却看到了
an even more dramatic rise
更大幅度的上升
as a consequence of OUR actions.
作为我们行动的结果。
We have increased the numbers of a few species
我们增加了一些物种的数量
almost astronomically.
几乎是天文数字。
CHICKS CHEEP
小鸡叽叽喳喳
By weight,
按重量计算，
70% of the world's birds are now chickens
现在世界上70%的鸟类是鸡
or other domesticated fowl.
或其他家禽。
We rear 70 billion farm animals each year...
我们每年饲养 700 亿头农场动物......
PIG GRUNTS
猪咕噜声
..and every one of them needs feeding.
……他们每个人都需要喂养。
Producing the food
生产食物
for such numbers of domesticated animals
对于如此数量的家养动物
is having a profound impact on the natural world.
对自然世界产生着深远的影响。
CHICKENS CLUCK
鸡叫声
The Amazon rainforest -
亚马逊雨林——
twice the size of India.
是印度面积的两倍。
It's so rich,
真是太丰富了，
it contains one in every ten species on the planet.
它包含了地球上十分之一的物种。
And it's home to this sloth and her ten-month-old baby.
这里是这只树懒和她十个月大的孩子的家。
He was born into an environment
他出生在一个环境
virtually untouched by humanity.
几乎没有受到人类的影响。
CHAINSAW BUZZES
电锯嗡嗡声
But now human beings are claiming even this space.
但现在人类甚至也声称拥有这个空间。
Year after year, we clear over two million hectares
年复一年，我们清理了超过 200 万公顷的土地
of the Amazon forest -
亚马逊森林——
an area the size of Wales.
面积相当于威尔士那么大。
And we use nearly all of it
我们几乎使用了所有这些
to make more space for cattle...
为牛腾出更多空间...
..and to grow soya to feed our livestock.
..并种植大豆来喂养我们的牲畜。
Today, habitat destruction is the biggest problem
如今，栖息地破坏是最大的问题
we have created for wildlife around the world.
我们为世界各地的野生动物创造了。
BRANCHES RUSTLE
树枝沙沙作响
This porcupine has survived the fire...
这只豪猪在火灾中幸存下来......
..and is being rescued.
……正在获救。
It's being relocated to pristine forests.
它正在被迁移到原始森林。
This will be its new home.
这将是它的新家。
Only a fortunate few animals
只有少数幸运的动物
are being given such a second chance.
正在被给予这样的第二次机会。
A healthy natural world is not only vital for wildlife...
健康的自然世界不仅对野生动物至关重要……
..but for our own very existence.
..但为了我们自己的存在。
Somehow we must find ways to redress the balance.
我们必须以某种方式找到纠正平衡的方法。
Currently, the vast majority of agricultural land,
目前，绝大多数农业用地，
more than 75%,
超过75%，
is used to raise livestock,
用于饲养牲畜，
and this is very inefficient.
这是非常低效的。
There are solutions.
有解决方案。
One is considering what we eat.
一是考虑我们吃什么。
If we shift away from eating meat and dairy
如果我们不再吃肉类和奶制品
and move towards a plant-based diet,
并转向植物性饮食，
then the sun's energy goes directly into growing our food.
然后太阳的能量直接用于种植我们的食物。
And because that's so much more efficient,
因为这样效率更高
we could still produce enough to feed us,
我们仍然可以生产足够的食物来养活我们，
but do so using a quarter of the land.
但这样做需要使用四分之一的土地。
This could free up an area the size of the United States,
这可以腾出相当于美国那么大的面积，
China, the European Union and Australia combined...
中国、欧盟和澳大利亚联合...
..space that could then be given back to nature.
..然后可以回归自然的空间。
And human innovations may be able
人类的创新也许能够
to do even more for wildlife.
为野生动物做更多的事情。
High-tech farms now grow plants vertically,
高科技农场现在垂直种植植物，
yielding up to 350 times the food grown in the same area.
产量是同一地区种植粮食的 350 倍。
This is one of many solutions we already have,
这是我们已有的众多解决方案之一，
and others are surely on the horizon.
其他的肯定也即将出现。
To find ways to protect all life on Earth
寻找保护地球上所有生命的方法
means reimagining how we live on this planet in the future.
意味着重新想象我们未来如何在这个星球上生活。
Human ingenuity,
人类的聪明才智，
our extraordinary ability to find solutions,
我们寻找解决方案的非凡能力，
gives me hope that we can.
让我希望我们能做到。
It will be the major challenge
这将是重大挑战
for this generation and the next.
为了这一代和下一代。
幕后花絮
To film the impact
拍摄影响
that fires are having on the Amazon,
亚马逊雨林正在发生火灾，
the Planet Earth III team
地球脉动 III 团队
joined a local volunteer fire brigade.
加入了当地的志愿消防队。
The fire brigade are responding to a patch
消防队正在响应补丁
of primary rainforest that is burning.
正在燃烧的原始雨林。
It's been burning for two days now.
现在已经烧了两天了。
It's difficult to know what we're going to see.
很难知道我们会看到什么。
The fires are mainly lit illegally...
火灾主要是非法纵火...
..to clear space for cattle.
..为牛清理空间。
真的很激烈
看看那边的火
我以前从未见过这样的事
来吧，用水泵
从远处做
把拐角处的火停下来
Battling fires is dangerous work.
扑灭火灾是一项危险的工作。
But the firefighters face them every day.
但消防员每天都会面对他们。
For the wildlife film crew,
对于野生动物电影摄制组来说，
this is a totally new experience.
这是一种全新的体验。
And these fires can be unpredictable.
这些火灾可能是不可预测的。
Neil, don't spend long in there.
尼尔，别在那里呆太久。
我们需要小心，这样火就不会烧到这里
现在的风很危险
我认为我们；我们得跑了
我知道时间流逝
Oh!
哦！
往这边跑
这很可怕
With the ground team retreating,
随着地面部队的撤退，
the safest way to carry on filming is with the drone.
最安全的拍摄方式是使用无人机。
Have we lost the drone? I think Abi has seen it.
我们失去了无人机吗？
我想阿比已经看到了。
Abi is on her way.
阿比正在赶来的路上。
Can you confirm you're on your way to the drone, Abi?
阿比，你能确认你正在前往无人机的路上吗？
无人机已经起火
MAN SHOUTS
男人喊叫
我有无人机
它在我们面前坠毁了
它着火了
The drone is damaged beyond repair.
无人机已损坏且无法修复。
Don't worry about it. I mean it.
别担心。
我是认真的。
Don't worry about it. It's absolutely fine.
别担心。
绝对没问题。
It's not OK. It is. It's OK.
这不行。
这是。
没关系。
It's equipment. We've got a spare.
是装备啊
我们有一个备用的。
The main thing is, we're all safe. No-one's hurt.
最重要的是，我们都很安全。
没有人受伤。
The team regroup...
球队重新集结……
..and decide to move away from the heart of the fire
..并决定远离火源
to its fringes
到它的边缘
to look for animals caught up in the flames.
寻找被火焰困住的动物。
There's been reports of a monkey in the trees, so...
有报道称树上有一只猴子，所以...
Ah!
啊!
THEY SPEAK PORTUGUESE
他们说葡萄牙语
The problem is, there's fires all the way along here,
问题是这里一路上都着火
as well as all along here, so...
以及一直在这里，所以...
It's hard to know what all this wildlife is going to do
很难知道这些野生动物会做什么
when their home is burnt up like this.
当他们的家被烧成这样的时候。
I don't know what it's like for these rainforest animals
我不知道这些雨林动物的感受如何
to be experiencing a fire.
遭遇火灾。
It's horrific for me, so...
这对我来说太可怕了，所以...
..I don't know what it is for them.
……我不知道这对他们来说意味着什么。
The fires burn into the night.
大火一直燃烧到深夜。
The following day,
第二天，
the crew accompany the firefighters
船员陪同消防员
in the search for animals in the aftermath.
灾后寻找动物的过程中。
Oh, my God, there are flames all inside of it.
天哪，里面全是火焰。
Little termite...
小白蚁...
Oh, my God!
我的天啊！
Remarkably, some animals have survived.
值得注意的是，一些动物幸存下来。
对我来说很痛苦
因为大自然是有生命的，就像我们一样
我们所拥有的一切，它也拥有
所以看到这样的森林很难过
受罚应该！但不应该这样对待
它一定很强壮
给我们力量
因为如果它变弱，我们就会感觉更弱
如果它倒下了，我们都会倒下
Clearing land for farming
清理土地用于农业
is not a problem unique to the Amazon.
这并不是亚马逊独有的问题。
Agriculture now takes up half of the habitable land
农业现在占据了一半的可居住土地
on the planet.
在这个星球上。
To produce food with less impact on the natural world
生产对自然世界影响较小的食品
requires new approaches.
需要新的方法。
And that led the wildlife film crew to a farm
这让野生动物电影摄制组来到了一个农场
in a warehouse.
在一个仓库里。
We're in the middle of the city!
我们在市中心！
I can't believe so much food
我简直不敢相信有这么多食物
being grown in such a small space!
竟然在这么小的空间里生长！
Here in Los Angeles, 6,000 miles from the Amazon,
在距离亚马逊 6,000 英里的洛杉矶，
this farm is part of a burgeoning food revolution.
这个农场是蓬勃发展的食品革命的一部分。
This is the most productive farm in the world,
这是世界上生产力最高的农场，
and it's our goal to reduce the amount of land and resources
我们的目标是减少土地和资源的数量
necessary to grow down to the bare minimum.
必须增长到最低限度。
It took a while to understand that, for nature,
我花了一段时间才明白，对于大自然来说，
agricultural use of land
农业用地
was the primary, like, destructive behaviour of humanity.
是人类主要的破坏性行为。
As we expand this means of growing,
当我们扩大这种增长方式时，
I'm very hopeful that this approach can ultimately
我非常希望这种方法最终能够
give a lot of land back to nature
让大量土地回归自然
and allow that biodiversity to re-establish and flourish.
并让生物多样性得以重建和繁荣。
Not only does this farm use less space...
这个农场不仅占用的空间更少......
..but it also uses 90% less water,
..但它的用水量也减少了 90%，
no pesticides,
没有农药，
and cuts food miles.
并减少食物里程。
It does feel like a really good start.
这确实感觉像是一个很好的开始。
Ideas like this can reduce our footprint on the planet,
像这样的想法可以减少我们在地球上的足迹，
giving the natural world a chance to bounce back.
给自然世界一个反弹的机会。
Next time,
下次，
the heroes on the frontline saving wildlife.
奋战在前线拯救野生动物的英雄们。
They're exploring remote jungles...
他们正在探索偏远的丛林......
..working undercover to catch criminals...
..卧底抓捕罪犯...
..and leading endangered creatures to safety.
..并将濒临灭绝的生物引导到安全的地方。
Habitat Explorer brings animals and their habitats to life.
栖息地探索者让动物及其栖息地栩栩如生。
Explore this free interactive and make origami animals.
探索这个免费的互动并制作折纸动物。
Go to...
去...
..and follow the links to the Open University.
..然后点击开放大学的链接。
Or to order a free printed version, visit the website
或者要订购免费印刷版，请访问网站
or call the number on the screen.
或拨打屏幕上的号码。